<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Architecture</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Sample setup architecture">
    <p>
    	The following diagram shows a good example setup of a secured CA with external OCSP responders
    	and an external RA server that receives certificate requests. The request are periodically 
    	pulled by the CA and responses returned to the external RA. 
    	No network traffic flows from the right the left across FW2.
    </p>
    <p>
    <img src="images/sample-full-setup.jpg" alt="EJBCA sample setup" />
    </p>
  </section>

  <section name="External RA">
    <p>
In some cases, for security reasons, is it preferable to deny all inbound traffic to the CA and instead let the CA periodically 
fetch and process information from external trusted data sources. 
For an overview of the solution see the illustration below.
</p><p>
The ExtRA API contains the most basic functions like:
<ul>
    <li>Generate Certificate from PKCS10</li>
    <li>Generate PKCS12 for the end user</li>
    <li>KeyRecovery of the users key (if requested using PKCS12)</li>
    <li>Edit users</li>
    <li>Revoke Certificates</li>
</ul>
From EJBCA 3.10 the External RA API is bundled as a part of EJBCA and can be enabled in conf/externalra.properties. 
</p>
    <p>
    <img src="images/extra-architecture.jpg" alt="EJBCA with External RA" />
    </p>
<subsection name="External RA Service Workers">
<p>
External RA Service Workers are configured in the Admin GUI (described in the <a href="adminguide.html#External RA API">Admin Guide</a>).
Each worker will poll a DataSource in the application server.
The DataSource should point to a database outside the CA's network security zone.
Currently only soft PKCS#12 keystore for decryption and signing responses are supported.
</p><p>
A message in the database can contain one or more submessages.
If a worker find a new requests message it changes the status of the message to 'in process' and
extracts all sub-messages. For each submessage the worker will:
<ol>
    <li>decrypt the submessage with a keystore (or reject it if encryption is required)</li>
    <li>verify and validate the signature of the submessage (or reject it if signing is required)</li>
    <li>process the request in the submessage with the signers admin privileges (or with full privileges if no signature is present)</li>
    <li>sign the response submessage (if signatures are required by the Service Worker)</li>
    <li>encrypts the response submessage (if encryption is required by the Service Worker)</li>
</ol>
and finally write all the response submessages as single message with status 'processed' back to the DataSource.
Encryption in submessages are done using CMS/PKCS#7 envelopes. 
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="External RA API clients">
<p>
External RA API clients creates a message from several submessages, where each submessage
<ol>
    <li>contains a request</li>
    <li>is signed with the RA keystore (optional if not required by Service Worker)</li>
    <li>is encrypted with the Service Worker's keystore certificate (optional if not required by Service Worker)</li>
</ol>
The message is then written to the database polled by a External RA Service Worker.
After a while (depending on how often the Service Worker runs and if the CA is online) the client
can fetch the response message.
</p><p>
The client is also responsible for polling the database for responses from the External RA Service Worker.
</p>

</subsection>
  </section>

  <section name="Internal architecture">
    <p>
    	The following diagram is a very rough schema of the current architecture of EJBCA.
    </p>
    <p>
    <img src="images/architecture.gif" alt="EJBCA architecture" />
    </p>
    <p>
    	A more developer centric deployment diagram is given below. It displays the internal three layer architecture of EJBCA. The application is packages in an ear file. 
    	In this ear file various web applications (war files) handles the interfaces with the surrounding world, mostly through various web interfaces. 
    	The web applications uses ejb session beans to perform the business operations. The session beans in turn uses a persistence layer (data entities) to persist data in the database.    
    </p>
    <p> 
        You can add your own components by for example deploying another web application (external.war) in the application server, making use of the session bean API of EJBCA.
    </p>
    <p>
    <img src="images/DeploymentDiagram.png" alt="EJBCA deployment diagram" />
    </p>
  </section>

</body>
</document>

