<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Welcome</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Latest News">
    <note>
    EJBCA 3.2.1 is now available for <a
    href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=39716&amp;package_id=108797">download</a>.
    </note>
    <p>
    EJBCA 3.1 and later contains support for nCipher HSM. The development of this functionality was sponsored by 
    Linagora, <a href="http://www.linagora.com/">www.linagora.com</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
    New features in EJBCA 3.2 such as QC statement and external OCSP responders was sponsored by 
    CTec Security Solutions, <a href="http://www.commguard.com/">http://www.commguard.com/</a>.
    </p>
  </section>

<section name="EJBCA">
<p>
EJBCA is a fully functional Certificate Authority. Based on J2EE technology it constitutes a robust,
high performance and component based CA. Both flexible and platform independent, EJBCA can be used
standalone or integrated in any J2EE application.
</p>
<p>
EJBCA is an enterprise class PKI, meaning that you can use EJBCA to build a complete PKI infrastructure for your organisation.
If you only want to issue a few single certificates for testing, there are probably options that will get you started quicker, 
but if you want a serious PKI we recommend EJBCA.
</p>
<p>
You can use EJBCA to issue certificates for different purposes such as:
<ul>
<li>Strong authentication for users accessing your intranet/extranet/internet resources.</li>
<li>Secure communication with SSL servers and SSL clients.</li>
<li>Smart card based login to Windows and/or Linux.</li>
<li>Signing and enrypting email.</li>
<li>VPN connections by issuing certificates to your VPN routers such as OpenVPN, Cisco, Juniper etc.</li>
<li>Client VPN access with certificates in users VPN clients.</li>
<li>Single sign-on by using a single certificate to secure logon to web applications.</li>
<li>Creating signed documents.</li>
<li>Issue citizen certificates for access to government resourses, used in passports etc.</li>
<li>... and many many more ...</li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>
<section name="Open Source">
<p>
This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software.
OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.
</p>
<p>
The source code of EJBCA is hosted on <a href="http://www.sf.net/">Sourceforge.net</a> and all downloads include the complete source code.
<br></br>
If you want to contribute to EJBCA, please see <i><a href="donations.html">Contribute to EJBCA</a></i>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Support and development">
<p>Commercial support, development and integration for EJBCA is available through <a href="http://www.primekey.se/">PrimeKey Solutions</a>. 
</p>
</section>


</body>
</document>

