<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Security</title>
  </properties>
<body>
<section name="EJBCA SECURITY">
<p>
Security is CRITICAL for a CA. Protection of the CAs private key is essential,
 since compromise of the CAs private key will let anyone issue false
 certificates, which can be used to gain access to systems relying on the CA for
 authentication and other security services.
 </p>
 <p>
After realizing this, please read on and take a pragmatic approach to security
 suitable for your policy, application and environment.
</p></section>

<section name="Firewall ports">
<p>To have a functional EJBCA installation there are only two ports that need to be open to the outside:
<ul>
<li>8080 - the public HTTP port of you application server, used for clients to access the public web for enrollment.</li>
<li>8443 - the SSL protected HTTPS port used to access the admin GUI of EJBCA. This port requires client certificate for access.</li>
</ul>
Additional ports that you may need to open are SSH, outgoing SMTP, outgoing LDAP etc. Which additional ports that needs to be open depends on your specific setup and which 
services you use. You do not need outgoing SMTP if you don't use email notification for example.
</p>
<p>
Locally on the host a number of ports are used in order for your application server to function.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Securing JBoss">
<p>
JBoss has description how to secure a default installation of JBoss. You should read this document before putting
your application in production.
</p><p>
Check out: <a href="http://community.jboss.org/wiki/SecureJBoss">SecureJBoss</a>
</p>
<p>You should at least disable the public admin console by removing jmx-console.war, management/console-mgr.sar and 
jbossweb-tomcat55.sar/ROOT.war from deploy.
</p>
<p>Alternatively protect it with a password set in
jboss/server/default/deploy/management/console-mgr.sar/web-console.war/WEB-INF/classes/web-console-users.properties
</p>
<p>You should also make sure all sensitive files can only be read by the JBoss user. These files are for example the server.xml 
file where the password for the SSL keystores are stored.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Setting up SSL">
<p>
To set upp SSL communication for all HTTP traffic to the server 
follow the instructions for installing EJBCA, this will set up HTTPS 
for the admin-GUI automatically.
 </p><p>
This will set up an SSL port open for the public at 8442 and an SSL port
which require client certificate to access the administration GUI at 8443.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Java truststore">
<p>
Acceptable CA certificates for clients are stored (by java) in $JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/security/cacerts. 
There are however many others present as shipped by Java, which means that anyone with a certificate issued 
by one of those CAs normally can access port 8443 on you JBoss server. They can not access the admin-GUI however,
since EJBCA checks authorization. 

When EJBCA deploys, it generates a custom truststore that is used by JBoss. 
So the certificates available in $JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/security/cacerts are NOT trusted.

If using another application server than JBoss, check the trust keystore contents of you application server so 
you don't trust too many issuers. 
</p>
<p>
You can create a new Java trust store with the command:
</p>
<source>
ant javatruststore
</source>
<p>
The trust store will be stored as p12/truststore.jks
</p>
<p>
Manual steps to creating a java trust store:
</p>
<source>
keytool -import -alias AdminCA1 -trustcacerts -file root.der -keystore /home/jboss/java/cacerts
</source>
<p>
Where root.der is the root certificate from EJBCA that you saved, for instance with the command:
</p>
<source>
bin/ejbca.sh ca getrootcert AdminCA1 root.der -der
</source>
<p>
AdminCA1 is the name of your CA that you are using for server and administrator certificates in EJBCA.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Configuring for security">
<p>
The easiest way to keep the installation secure is to block all default JBOSS ports
 (1099, 1476, 4444, 8082, 8083) from the outside and only allow traffic to Tomcat ports (8442 and 8443).
This is because the public end-user actions can be performed through the public
servlets, while administration tasks are performed directly on the beans.
</p>
<p>
See 'ejbcafirewall.sh' for an example how to configure an Iptables firewall in
Linux for protecting EJBCA running on JBoss.
</p>
<p>
See <a href="http://www.jboss.org/">JBoss documentation</a> for a list of ports used in JBoss, for information about
 security in JBOSS/EJB and for how to set up SSL with JBOSS.
See this <a href="http://www.javaworld.com/javaworld/jw-08-2001/jw-0831-jaas_p.html">JavaWorld article</a> for more
 examples about setting up role-permissions.
</p>
</section>

<section name="File permission">
<p>
The application server should be run as a special user. Files should be protected 
so the ONLY the user running the application server can access them. 
</p><p>
By default JBoss is probably unpacked with read access to all, you should issue:
</p>
<source>
umask 077
chmod -R go-rwx *
</source>
<p>
In the JBOSS_HOME directory, to make the files readable only by the jboss user, and make this the default permission
for files copied here.
</p>
<p>
If PKCS12 files are generated for users, the subdirectory ('p12') where
they are stored and the generated files should be protected in the same way.
</p></section>

<section name="User authentication">
<p>
Default user authentication for enrollment in EJBCA is done with a one-time
password scheme. When a user has enrolled for a certificate his status is
set to GENERATED and the password can not be used again to enroll for a new
certificate. An administrator must re-set the users status and preferably
set a new password.
</p><p>

If implementing other user authentication scenarios you should remember
that certificate authentication is stronger than password based
authentication (for example LDAP). If EJBCA users authenticate 
with some other (not one-time) password instead of usual one-time password, 
a strong authentication mechanism will be build on a weaker one.
</p></section>

<section name="Passwords defined when configuring EJBCA.">
<p>
The configuration files (in $EJBCA_HOME/conf) contains some passwords.
It is not considered to be a security risk to declare all these passwords
in clear text. Anyone that could log on to the server with EJBCA could apart from
reading these files also do anything he wants with the CLI of EJBCA. If an unauthorized
person could use the CLI this is severe security risk. But reading the passwords is not
much of a problem since the passwords in any case can not be used to anything outside
the server.
</p><p>
It is very important to restrict the access to the server only to a very few trust-able
persons.
</p><p>
If you anyway want to do something about these passwords the subsections of these section
is describing what could be done:
</p>
<subsection name="Passwords used by EJBCA taken from property files">
<p>
Some of the passwords are used directly by EJBCA code.
All these passwords may be configured encrypted in the same way as
<a href="adminguide.html#Auto-activation of CA tokens">PINs used for auto activation could be encrypted</a>.
</p>
<p>
List of these passwords in ejbca.properites :
<br/>ca.tokenpassword
<br/>ca.keystorepass
<br/>ca.ocspkeystorepass
<br/>ca.xkmskeystorepass
<br/>ca.cmskeystorepass
</p><p>
List of these passwords in protectedlog.properties :
<br/>protectionTokenKeyStorePassword
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Passwords used by the application server">
<p>
Some of the passwords is not used by EJBCA but by the application server. If this passwords
should be encrypted it must be in a way so that they could be decrypted by the application
server. You have to consult the documentation of the application server to find out how to
encrypt them (example: <a href="#Datasource passwords">datasource password in jboss</a>).
</p><p>
This are these passwords:
<br/>mail.password in mail.properties
<br/>database.password in database.properties
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Passwords prompted for by 'ant install'">
<p>
If you don't define superadmin.password in web.properties then 'ant install' will prompt for it.
Since this password does not has to be known by EJBCA after the super admin token has been created
it will not exist in any file after the installation.
</p>
<p>
The passwords java.trustpassword and httpsserver.password also in web.properties are used to generate
keystore files at 'ant install'. These passwords must later on be specified in the application server
configuration. If these passwords are not specified and the property 'web.promptForPassword' is set to
'true' then these passwords are also prompted for.
</p><p>
But if you let 'ant install' prompt for these passwords you must set them (maybe encrypted if possible)
in the application server configuration. The file for the application server is copied to the application
server at 'ant deploy' (in jboss 4.2.3 the file is called $JBOSS_HOME/server/default/deploy/jboss-web.deployer/server.xml)
You must then manually substitute the strings 'changeThisToThePassword' in the configuration file with clear
text or possible encrypted (application server specific) passwords.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section name="Datasource passwords">
<p>
If you do not like to have your DataSource password available in clear text in EjbcaDS.xml, 
there is an article in the JBoss Wiki about encrypting them:
<br/>
<a href="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=EncryptingDataSourcePasswords">
http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=EncryptingDataSourcePasswords</a>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Database privileges">
<p>
During the installation process of EJBCA, JBoss creates all the required database
tables. To do this the EJBCA-database user has to have CREATE TABLE privileges. During
upgrades EJCBA needs CREATE and ALTER TABLE privileges. (SELECT, UPDATE, INSERT and DELETE
privileges are also required.)
</p><p>
After the installation during normal operations only regular SELECT, UPDATE, INSERT
and DELETE commands are needed. The table LogEntryData will only be used with SELECT and
INSERT.
</p><p>
Instead of changing the privileges of the EJBCA-user, it's recommended to have two
different users "ejbca" and "ejbca-admin". For regular operations "ejbca" is used, but
for the installation and upgrades, EJBCA is re-deployed with "ejbca-admin" configured
in conf/database.properties. 
</p>
</section>

<section name="SSL connections in MySQL">
<p>
<a href="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.0/en/secure-using-ssl.html">
http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.0/en/secure-using-ssl.html</a>
<a href="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.1/en/secure-using-ssl.html">
http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.1/en/secure-using-ssl.html</a>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Other precautions">
<subsection name="Switching to production mode">
<p>
Switching to production mode by setting ejbca.productionmode in conf/ejbca.properties
will prevent ant from starting JUnit tests and deploying the CA build on an OCSP responder
and vice versa.   
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Database transaction logs in MySQL">
<p>
<a href="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.0/en/binary-log.html">
http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.0/en/binary-log.html</a>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="System accounting in Linux">
<p>
See your distribution for details about their package, below are general links.
<br/>
<a href="http://www.nic.com/~dave/SecurityAdminGuide/SecurityAdminGuide-5.html">
http://www.nic.com/~dave/SecurityAdminGuide/SecurityAdminGuide-5.html</a>
<a href="http://www.hsc.fr/ressources/presentations/linux2000/linux2000-18.html.en">
</a>
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section name="Denial of Service">
    <subsection name="Due too large data packages">
        <p>
            There is no way to limit the datapackages reaching JBoss through a HTTP request from within JBoss. 
            This is due to the way the TCP protocol works. 
            The best way to avoid this kind of DOS attacks is to use a firewall or proxy that can limit the size of request and configure it properly.
        </p>
    </subsection>
</section>

</body>
</document>

