<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>VA Services</title>
  </properties>
<body>
<section name="VA Services">
<p>
The validation authority (VA) module of EJBCA provides services used to validate a certificate. These services can run on an
installed EJBCA or on a <a href="installation-va.html">standalone VA installation</a>.
Each service can be enabled/disabled independently at compile time. The services are disabled by default.
</p>
<subsection name="CA certificate store">
<p>
The CA certificate store is used to get a certificate chain to the root CA in order to verify that the certificate is
signed by a valid CA (it is valid if the root is trusted).
<a href="#RFC 4387">RFC 4387</a> specifies how the certificates are retrieved.
The configuration file conf/certstore.properties is used to configure the service.
</p><p>
If you view the page <strong>http://vahost:8080/certificates/search.cgi</strong> (when the service is enabled) you will get links to all URLs that can be used.
'certificates' is the default URL path for the web module, but this can be changed in the configuration.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="CRL store">
<p>
The CRL store is used to get a Certificate Revocation List (a signed list of revoked certificates) for a CA.
<a href="#RFC 4387">RFC 4387</a> specifies how the CRLs are retrieved.
The configuration file conf/crlstore.properties is used to configure the service.
</p><p>
If you view the page <strong>http://vahost:8080/crls/search.cgi</strong> you will get links to all URLs that could be used.
'crls' is the default path for the web module, but this can be changed in the configuration.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="OCSP responder">
<p>
The OCSP responder is used to ask if a certificate is revoked or not. The OCSP protocol is specified in <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2560.txt">RFC 2560</a>.
See <a href="architecture-ocsp.html">OCSP Architecture</a>
</p>
<p>The url for OCSP services is <strong>http://vahost:8080/ejbca/publicweb/status/ocsp</strong>
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="RFC 4387">
<p>
The protocol to retrieve CRLs and certificates is described in <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4387">RFC 4387</a>.
</p><p>
Only CA certificates can be fetched. Since the attributes 'certHash', 'uri', 'iAndSHash' and 'name' does not make that much sense to CA
certificates and CRLs they are not implemented.
</p><p>
To be able to specify that a delta CRL should be fetched an extra parameter 'delta' is added to the URL. This is not described in the RFC.
Example:
</p>
<source>
http://myhost:8080/crls/search.cgi?sKIDHash=X4NX3VF9u/tzkkGZU6M6OEffhFc&amp;delta=
</source>
<p>
When searching for certificates you can use iHash, sHash and sKIDHash. iHash is the ASN1 encoded DN of the issuer in a certificate. If you search with it you get all certificates that has the same issuer, except for the root certificate.
You do not find a root certificate if you search with the iHash of the root. It has been assumed that sHash should be used when searching for a root.
</p>
<p>
If you want to implement your own application accessing the VA you could look at the ejbca junit test class org.ejbca.ui.web.protocol.CertStoreServletTest
</p>
</section>

</body>

</document>

