<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Certificate Authority enrollment</title>
  </properties>

<body>
<section name="Certificate Authority enrollment">
<p>
Certificate authorities create,
verify, renew, revoke, and reissue certificates. We are now using the
Enterprise Java Bean Certificate Authority (EJBCA) via a secure (https)
SSL connection.
</p>
<p>
Because we wish to tightly
control who gets a SensorNet certificate, you will receive an
invitation to get a SensorNet certificate. This will come by e-mail or
surface mail.
</p>
<warning>It is vital that you import your certificate on a properly secured computer.</warning>
<p>
This means up-to date security patches, anti-virus, and anti-pest
programs. Otherwise, your private key will be at risk, and security
will be compromised. We strongly recommend that you use Firefox,
Firefox, or Netscape 7.x because they handle certificates much better
than Internet Explorer and have many fewer security holes.
</p>
<subsection name="FireFox">
<p>Open the URL in your mail message to see the screen in Figure 1.</p>

<img alt="CA welcome page" src="CAwelcome.png"/>

<p>
Click the for your browser link and enter the
username and password that were in your e-mail (Figure 2), and click OK to generate your key pair.
</p>
<p>
	<img alt="Enrollment form" src="CertificateEnrollment.png"/>
</p>
<p>
	<img alt="Generating key pair" src="keygen.png"/>
</p>
<p>
When the key generation is finished, in Firefox, you are done.
<warning>Do not press the OK Button a second time! </warning>Firefox
may ask you to create a password to protect your key store. Choose a
good password (at least 8 characters containing letters, numbers,
special characters and no dictionary words) and remember it. You will
have to supply this password whenever the certificate is used. Firefox
uses this same password to protect other sensitive information you ask
the browser to save, such as site passwords. Now learn to <a
 href="MozillaHowTo/MozillaCertificateManagement.html">manage your
certificates in Firefox</a>.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Microsoft Internet Explorer">
<p>
if you used Internet Explorer
(IE), the situation is different (Figure 4). Be sure to choose the
Microsoft enhanced Cryptographic Provider v1.0 in the drop-down box.
When you click OK, the "Creating a new RSA exchange key" pop-up will
appear. <span style="font-weight: bold;">It is essential that you
press the "Set Security Level" button.</span> Otherwise, your private
key will not be protected by a password. Be sure to choose the High
security level.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="Saving a new certificate in Internet Explorer" src="IECertSave.png"/>
</p>
<p>
You will then be asked for a
password to protect your certificate and then make sure that the "<span
 style="font-weight: bold;">Creating a new Exchange key"</span> dialog
shows that the protection level is set to <span
 style="font-weight: bold;">High</span> (Figure 5). If you have XP
Service Pack 2, several warning pop-ups may appear about allowing
untrusted sites to install certificates. You trust us, so check <span
 style="font-weight: bold;">OK</span> if they appear.
</p>
<p>
<img alt="The security level is now high" src="IELevelHigh.png"/>
</p>
<p>
The import process is now complete (Figure 6).
</p>
<p>
<img alt="IE import successful" src="IEImportDone.png" />
</p>
</subsection>


</section>



</body>
</document>


