<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Standalone VA Installation</title>
  </properties>
<body>
<section name="Standalone VA Installation">
  <subsection name="Building and configuring EJBCA">
  <p>
EJBCA should be configured as for any other installation but you must also set all preferences
of the VA database in conf/va-publisher.properties. 
The VA database is the master database of all standalone VA installations. It is there that EJBCA will 
publish certificates when they are issued or revoked. 
</p><p>
After this configuration EJBCA is built and deployed as usual with the commands 'ant deploy', 'ant web-configure', and 'ant deploy-keystore', as described in the EJBCA installation guide.
</p><p>
The deploy command sets up a datasource <b>java:/OcspDS</b> in JBoss, if you use another application server 
you must set up this datasource manually. It should be a datasource that is not involved in transactions
(a <i>no-tx-datasource</i> in JBoss), and it should have autocommit (should be default in JBoss).
</p><p>
When EJBCA has been started you have to add a new publisher. As a superadministrator you add this publisher
on the "Edit Publishers" page in the Admin GUI. Use publisher type "Validation Authority Publisher". 
</p>
<p>
Validation Authority Settings :
</p>
<ul>
<li>'Data Source' - is the database of the standalone VA where this publisher will publish certificates. Use java:/OcspDS if ocsp-datasource.jndi-name=OcspDS.</li>
<li>'Store certificate at the Validation Authority' - stores the complete certificate on the VA. If this is unchecked only the information needed to answer OCSP requests are stored, but not the certificate itself.
There are good reasons not to publish the whole certificate. It is large, thus making it a bit of heavy insert and it may contain sensitive information. 
On the other hand some OCSP Extension plug-ins may not work without the certificate. A regular OCSP responder works fine without the certificate. A publisher for CA certificates (used on a 'Edit Certificate Authorities' page) must have this enabled.
</li>
<li>'Publish only revoked certificates' - If checked only revoked certificate are stored on the VA. The OCSP responder of the VA must have the 'nonexistingisgood' (conf/ocsp.properties) enabled if only revoked certificates are published.
A publisher for CA certificates (used on a 'Edit Certificate Authorities' page) must have this disabled.</li>
<li>'Store CRL at the Validation Authority' - should be set if the CRL store service of the VA should be used for a CA (only has a meaning for publishers used on a 'Edit Certificate Authorities' page).</li>
</ul>
<p>
All certificate profiles for certificates that should be available to the OCSP responder should
have a reference to this publisher. To configure this you must be a superadministrator.
</p><p>
All CAs that should have their certificates and CRLs published to the VA  should
have a reference to this publisher. To configure this you must be a superadministrator.
</p><p>
When all settings above have been done, every issued or revoked certificate with a certificate
profile that uses the ValidationAuthorityPublisher should be published in the responder
database as well as in the EJBCA database.
If the publishing is not working it is important to notice this and synchronize the databases again, 
see <a href="#Error%20handling">Error handling</a> below.
  </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Building and configuring the VA">
  <p>
The VA is configured using the same configuration files as EJBCA. 
Only the preferences ocsp.*, crlstore.*, certstore.*, httpsserver.* and database.* are relevant to the responder but you may keep conf/*.properties
from the EJBCA setup since definitions of other properties does no harm.<br/>
</p>
<note> 
Note that the standalone VA uses the configuration options database.* and not the ocsp-database.* options to access the VA database.
</note>
<p>
Please read description of the configuration properties in conf/ocsp.properties.sample, conf/database.properties.sample, conf/crlstore.properties.sample, conf/certstore.properties.sample and perhaps 
conf/web.properties.sample (if SSL or different ports should be configured).
</p><p>
For the certificate and CRL store service the sample file should be enough to understand how to set it up. For the OCSP responder service there is separate <a href="installation-ocsp.html">setup instructions</a> for the Standalone OCSP installation.

</p><p>
The validation authority is built and deployed with (keystore step is not required if you you have disabled SSL in web.properties):
</p><source>
ant va-deploy
ant deploy-keystore
ant web-configure
</source>
<p>
on the VA server.
</p>

<subsubsection name="Responder database">
<p>
The standalone VA database (that OcspDS in EJBCA and EjbcaDS in standalone VA points to) only have to contain the CertificateData and CRLData table. These tables are 
created automatically by JBoss when it starts on the standalone VA.
</p><p>
The database connection settings on the standalone VA is configured and deployed in JBoss in the file 
JBOSS_HOME/server/default/deploy/ejbca-ds.xml.
</p>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="Error handling">
<p>
If there is an error publishing to the VA database, the VA/OCSP Responder will be out of sync with the CA.
It is very important to re-synchronize the databases in that case.
</p>
<p>
In case of failure to publish to the VA database the following error message will appear in the server log on the EJBCA
server:
</p>
<source>
Validation Authority ERROR, publishing is not working
</source>
<p>
This will be followed by more details of the error.
</p><p>
The log must be monitored to discover such a fault and if such a fault is discovered an alarm should notify 
the operator that he has to fix whatever is wrong and then synchronise the VA database with the EJBCA 
database (see 'Synchronise the database of the responder').
  </p>
  
  <subsection name="Synchronise the database of the responder">
  <p>
At the beginning and after failure in publishing to the VA responder, the master database of the
publishers must be synchronised with the CertificateData and CRLData table of the database of EJBCA.
If you only use OCSP and not CRL store, only the CertificateData table needs to be synchronised.
</p><p>
If there is a single certificate out of sync you can re-sync it by doing a 'Republish' from the admin-GUI.
</p><p>
The following procedure may be used to synchronise the database of EJBCA with the database of the
responder:
</p><p>
<b>1.</b> Prevent any further issuing of new certificates and revocation of old certificates until the
synchronisation is finished. This might be done by simply blocking the port to the adminweb.
<br/>
<b>2.</b> On the host of ejbca the following commands can be used to make the synchronisation:
Run on the OCSP responder machine (as root user in mysql):
</p>
<source>
mysqladmin drop ocsp_db;
mysqladmin create ocsp_db;
</source><p>
This drops and re-creates the ocsp database to clean it. Replace ocsp_db with the database name of your database.
<br/>
Run on the CA server:
</p>
<source>
mysqldump -u ejbca -p --compress ejbca_db CertificateData > CertificateData.dat
mysqldump -u ejbca -p --compress ejbca_db CRLData > CRLData.dat
cat CertificateData.dat | mysql -h ocspresponder ocsp_db
cat CRLData.dat | mysql -h ocspresponder ocsp_db
</source>
<p>
Replace your the username ejbca with your username.
ocspresponder is the external VA/OCSP responder host.
</p>
<note>
Note, that this can usually not be done from a windows machine, to a Linux machine, because windows is not case sensitive.
</note>
<p>
<b>3.</b> Check that the publishing is working before allowing issuing and revoking.
  </p>
  </subsection>
</section>

<section name="Security considerations">
<subsection name="Database privileges">
<p>
Since the VA itself only reads from the database you should consider using a read-only database user for the VA.
The only write access needed to the database is the VA Publisher configured on the CA.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="Monitoring and healthcheck">
<p>There exists a health check service that can be used for health monitoring. 
It is also used for clusters, as it can be checked by load balancers to determine if a node should be active in the cluster (healthy) 
or taken out of the cluster (unhealthy). 
</p><p>
The servlet is located in the URL: http://127.0.0.1:8080/ejbca/publicweb/vahealthcheck/vahealth
and is configured using conf/ejbca.properties and conf/va.properties.
</p><p>
The following generic configuration parameters may be set in ejbca.properties to configure authorization and what the service checks:
</p>
<ul>
<li>healthcheck.amountfreemem, default: '1' - The number of Mb of memory that must be free.</li>
<li>healthcheck.dbquery, default: 'select 1' - Parameter indicating the string that should be used to do a minimal check that the database is working.</li>
<li>healthcheck.authorizedips, default: '127.0.0.1' - Specifies which remote IPs that may call this healthcheck servlet. Use ';' between multiple IPs.</li>
</ul>
<p>
The following configuration parameters may be set in va.properties to what the service checks:
</p>
<ul>
<li>ocsphealthcheck.signtest; default: 'true' - if the check of VA signing tokens should actually perform a signature test, or it should only see if the token status is active.</li>
<li>ocsphealthcheck.checkSigningCertificateValidity, default: 'true' - if the healthcheck should check the validity of all signing certificates and give an error if a signing certificate has expored.</li>
</ul>
<p>By editing a maintenance file on the server, you can make the service return an error message stating that the server is down for mainenance.
This is very useful in a cluster when you can take cluster nodes in and out of rotation by editing a simple text file.
The following configuration parameters may be set in ejbca.properties:
</p>
<ul>
<li>healthcheck.maintenancefile, default: not set - location of file containing information about maintenance.</li>
<li>healthcheck.maintenancepropertyname, default: DOWN_FOR_MAINTENANCE - the healthcheck.maintenancefile should contain a single line like this 'DOWN_FOR_MAINTENANCE=true'.</li>
</ul>
<p>The following parameters in ejbca.properties configure what message or HTTP error code the health service returns.
</p> 
<ul>
<li>healthcheck.okmessage, default: 'ALLOK' - Text string used to say that every thing is ok with this node.</li>
<li>healthcheck.sendservererror, default: 'true' - if a HTTP errorcode 500 should be sent in case of error.</li>
<li>healthcheck.customerrormessage, default: null - Set this parameter if you want a static error message instead of one generated by the HealthChecker.</li>
</ul>
<p>
If an error is detected one or several of the following error messages is reported.
</p>
<ul>
<li>"MEM: Error Virtual Memory is about to run out, currently free memory : number" - The JVM is about to run out of memory.</li>
<li>"DB: Error creating connection to database" - JDBC Connection to the database failed, this might occur if DB craches or network is down.</li>
<li>"MAINT: DOWN_FOR_MAINTENANCE" - This is reported when the healthcheck.maintenancefile is used and the node is set to be off line.</li>
<li>"OCSP signing key not usable for CA..." - This means that the signing token for a CA is offline and OCSP responses for that CA can not be signed.</li>
</ul>
</section>

</body>
</document>
