<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Standalone VA Installation</title>
  </properties>
<body>
<section name="Standalone VA Installation">
<p><b>1. On the EJBCA VA </b> - Configure the VA</p>
<p>
A Validation Authority installation is at first glance identical to a standard CA installation, but only a subset 
of services is activated in order to function as merely a VA. This means that an EJBCA installation could in practice 
be used as both its own CA and as a VA for another CA at the same time. 
</p>
<p>
The VA is configured using the same configuration files as EJBCA. Files that are of special interest to an installation 
acting as a VA are va.properties, ocsp.properties, crlstore.properties and certstore.properties.  For the certificate and 
CRL store service the sample file should be enough to understand how to set it up. For the OCSP responder, all default 
options for the OCSP behavior is set in conf/ocsp.properties and conf/va.properties. All options are documented in these files. 
In case of OCSP responder, you may also want to configure conf/cesecore.properties for "Secure audit log configuration", 
i.e. if you want to log to database or file. The database audit log is only used for security events, i.e. access control 
and configuration change events when using the GUI or CLI.
</p>
<p><b>2. On the EJBCA VA</b> - Build the VA</p>
<p>
The VA is build in the same way as the CA. So after starting JBoss, run the following command from EJBCA home directory:
</p>
<source>ant deploy</source> 
<p>
If you have not disabled SSL (by setting 'web.nosslconfigure' in web.properties file), you will need to copy tomcat.jks and 
truststore.jks from EJBCA_HOME/p12 directory on the CA to the EJBCA_HOME/p12 directory on the VA (You might need to configure 
web.properties to use the right passwords). Then, from EJBCA home directory, run the following commands:
</p>
<source>
ant deplpy-keystore
ant web-configure
</source>
<p><b>3. On the EJBCA CA</b> - Configure va-publisher.properties</p>
<p>
The EJBCA CA should be configured the same when installing a VA as for any other installation with the addition of setting preferences 
for the VA database in conf/va-publisher.properties. The VA database is the master database for the standalone VA installations and where 
the master CA will publish certificates when they are issued or revoked. 
</p>
<p>
In the case of the VA being an OCSP responder, the data source 'java:/OcspDS' should be set in JBoss. The VA data source should not be 
involved in transactions (a no-tx-datasource in JBoss), and it should have autocommit (should be default in JBoss). See 
<a href="installation.html#JBoss">Installation</a> for instruction on how to create this data source if needed.
</p>
<p><b>4. On the EJBCA CA</b> - Add a va-publisher</p>
<p>
Add a new publisher to the main CA server (not the VA). As a super administrator, you add this publisher on the "Edit Publishers" page 
in the Admin GUI. Use publisher type "Validation Authority Publisher" The settings for this publisher are as follows:
<ul>
    <li>'Data Source' - is the database of the standalone VA where this publisher will publish certificates. Use java:/OcspDS if 
    ocsp-datasource.jndi-name=OcspDS. This must be a non-tx/jta=false data source (see Installation for instruction how to create this 
    manually if needed).</li>
    <li>'Store certificate at the Validation Authority' - stores the complete certificate on the VA. If this is unchecked only the 
    information needed to answer OCSP requests are stored, but not the certificate itself. There are good reasons not to publish the whole 
    certificate. It is large, thus making it a bit of heavy insert and it may contain sensitive information. On the other hand some OCSP 
    Extension plug-ins may not work without the certificate. A regular OCSP responder works fine without the certificate. A publisher for 
    CA certificates (used on a 'Edit Certificate Authorities' page) must have this enabled.</li>
    <li>'Publish only revoked certificates' - If checked only revoked certificate are stored on the VA. The OCSP responder of the VA must 
    have the 'nonexistingisgood' (conf/ocsp.properties) enabled if only revoked certificates are published. A publisher for CA certificates 
    (used on a 'Edit Certificate Authorities' page) must have this disabled.</li>
    <li>'Store CRL at the Validation Authority' - should be set if the CRL store service of the VA should be used for a CA (only has a 
    meaning for publishers used on a 'Edit Certificate Authorities' page). In order to use this option you must also check 'Store certificate 
    at the Validation Authority', and you must not check 'Publish only revoked certificates'. This is because the CA certificate(s) must also 
    be stored in the VA when CRLs are stored there.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
All CAs that publish certificates and CRLs to the VA should have a reference to this publisher. To configure this you must be a super administrator.
</p>
<p>
If the VA is a certificate or a CRL store service, the installation of the VA is complete. If the VA is an OCSP responder, continue the installation 
by following the steps described in <a href="installation-ocsp.html">OCSP installation</a>. 
</p>

<subsection name="VA database">
<p>
Certificate revocation information for the VA services must be present in the database of the instance acting as VA/OCSP responder.
If the issuing CA and VA instances of EJBCA uses different databases, 'Publisher's are used to push real-time information from the CA to the VA database.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="Error handling">
<p>
If there is an error publishing to the VA database, the VA/OCSP Responder will be out of sync with the CA.
It is very important to re-synchronize the databases in that case.
</p>
<p>
In case of failure to publish to the VA database the following error message will appear in the server log on the EJBCA
server:
</p>
<source>
Validation Authority ERROR, publishing is not working
</source>
<p>
This will be followed by more details of the error.
</p>
<p>
The log must be monitored to discover such a fault and if such a fault is discovered an alarm should notify 
the operator that he has to fix whatever is wrong and then synchronise the VA database with the EJBCA 
database (see 'Synchronise the database of the responder').
</p>
  
  <subsection name="Synchronise the database of the responder">
  <p>
At the beginning and after failure in publishing to the VA responder, the master database of the
publishers must be synchronized with the CertificateData and CRLData table of the database of EJBCA.
If you only use OCSP and not CRL store, only the CertificateData table needs to be synchronized.
</p><p>
If there is a single certificate out of sync you can re-sync it by doing a 'Republish' from the AdminGUI.
</p><p>
The following procedure may be used to synchronize the database of EJBCA with the database of a pure VA instance
(e.g. where all certificates are issued on another instance):
</p><p>
The example is for MySQL and should be adapted to your environment (database, hostnames, database name and database credentials).
</p><p>
<b>1.</b> Prevent any further issuing of new certificates and revocation of old certificates until the
synchronization is finished. This might be done by simply blocking the port to the AdminGUI.
<br/>
<b>2.</b> On the host of CA the following commands can be used to make the synchronization:
Run on the OCSP responder machine (as root user in mysql):
</p>
<source>
mysql -u ejbca -p ocsp_db
mysql> drop table CertificateData;
mysql> drop table CRLData;
</source>
<p>
This drops and re-creates the tables containing certificate and CRL information. Run on the CA server:
</p>
<source>
mysqldump -u ejbca -p --compress ejbca_db CertificateData > CertificateData.dat
mysqldump -u ejbca -p --compress ejbca_db CRLData > CRLData.dat
cat CertificateData.dat | mysql -h ocspresponder ocsp_db
cat CRLData.dat | mysql -h ocspresponder ocsp_db
</source>
<note>
Note, that this can usually not be done from a windows machine, to a Linux machine, because windows is not case sensitive.
</note>
<p>
<b>3.</b> Check that the publishing is working before allowing issuing and revoking.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="Security considerations">
<subsection name="Database privileges">
<p>
Since a pure VA only reads from the database you should consider using a read-only database user for the VA.
The only write access needed to the database is the VA Publisher configured on the CA.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="Monitoring and healthcheck">
<p>
When OcspKeyBindings are used to respond to OCSP requests, the regular EJBA health-check will monitor that all marked as ACTIVE can be used to sign OCSP requests.
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
