<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Complementary software</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
<section name="Free software">
<p>
To build a successful PKI you can benefit from a lot of tools available. Here are listed some tools and packages that 
can be used together with PKI to even further improve your PKI experience.
</p>

<subsection name="Signserver">
    <p>
    <a href="http://www.signserver.org/">Signserver</a>
    </p>
    <p>
    The SignServer is an application for automatic signatures called by other systems not able to connect 
    to crytographic hardware. 
    It is a framework that can be customized to specific needs using simple plug-in modules. 
    The SignServer have a ready to use TimeStamp Authority (RFC 3161 compliant) and a MRTD Signer. 
    Another usage is to provide a simplified method to provide signatures in different application 
    managed from one location in the company.
    <br/>
    The SignServer have been designed for high-availability and can be clustered for maximum reliability.
    </p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Syscheck">
    <p>
    <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/syscheck/">Syscheck</a>
    </p>
	<p>
	It's a framework build with shell scripts to make sure a system is working and at good health. It started as checker for EJBCA. 
	Used in high security environments, that can not allow standard probes to be installed. The result is sent out with syslog. 	
	</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="CRL Publish Perl script">
    <p>
    <a href="http://search.cpan.org/~kcody/EJBCA-CrlPublish-0.50/">CRL Publish</a> perl script by Kevin Cody-Little.
    </p>
    <p>CRL Publish pushes newly generated CRLs to your distribution web servers. It can be installed from CPAN as module EJBCA::CrlPublish.
    </p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="CSRTool">
    <p>
    <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/csrtool">CSRTool at sourceforge</a>
    </p>
    <p>
    A graphical tool for generating RSA and ECDSA cryptographic key-pairs, creating Certificate Signing Requests (CSRs) from them, 
    and combining the key-pair with an issued digital certificate to create a secure portable container (PKCS12, JKS, JCEKS, etc.)    
    </p><p>
    Some features:
    <ul>
    <li>Generates RSA public and private key-pairs in sizes ranging from 1024 to 8192 bits.</li>
    <li>Generates Elliptic Curve DSA public and private key-pairs using either the ANSI X9.62 named curves, or custom parameters for your own curve if so inclined.</li>
    <li>Saves the private-key in a PKCS8 file with Password-Based-Encryption using the SHA1withTripleDES algorithm.</li>
    <li>Generates a PEM-encoded CSR that can be submitted to a CA either through a web-form or e-mail.</li>
    <li>Generates keyUsage and/or the subjectAltName extensions (optionally) in the RSA-based CSR.</li>
    <li>Combines the private-key from the previously-stored PKCS8 file and the newly returned digital certificate, into a PKCS12 file that can be used for importation into desired applications.</li>
    </ul>
    </p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Bouncycastle">
    <p>
    <a href="http://www.bouncycastle.org/">Bouncycastle website</a>
    </p>
    <p>
    Using Bouncycastle you can create your own tools and applications, or PKI enable your existing java applications.
    </p>
    <p>
    Bouncycastle also have a section with complementary packages (under resources) that you should look at.
    </p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="JMRTD">
	<p>
    <a href="http://www.jmrtd.org/">JMRTD website</a>
	</p>
	<p>
	JMRTD is a free implementation of the Machine Readable Travel Document (MRTD) standards as specified by the International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO). The electronic passport (or "ePassport"), which by now has been introduced in many countries, is an implementation of these standards.
	</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="ISODL">
	<p>
    <a href="http://isodl.sourceforge.net/">ISO18013 Electronic Driving License</a>
	</p>
	<p>
	Implements CVC certificates for driving licenses, using a slightly modified version of cert-cvc.
	</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="jSCEP">
	<p>
    <a href="http://code.google.com/p/jscep/">Java SCEP implementation</a>
	</p>
	<p>
	jSCEP is an open-source Java implementation of the Simple Certificate Enrollment Protocol (SCEP). It is capable of supporting both client- and server-side operations.
	</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="OpenSC">
	<p>
    <a href="http://www.opensc-project.org/">OpenSC project</a>
	</p>
	<p>
	OpenSC provides a set of libraries and utilities to work with smart cards. You can use OpenSC to support login and authentication using PKI smart cards.
	</p>
</subsection>

</section>

<section name="Hardware tokens">

<subsection name="SecureMetric">
	<p>
	<a href="http://www.securemetric.com">SecureMetric</a> has over 13 years experience in serving clients across the world and the market leader in the Smart Card and Cryptographic Token industry for the Southeast Asian region. Our flagship SecureToken ST3 is a lightweight PKI token that is cost effective and has been proven to work better than other well known international brands.
	</p>
	<p>
	When deployed together with our Token Management and Registration Authority (TMS-RA) system, we are able to unify the separated Certificate and Token life cycles into a single management system which allows operators to better manage their clients and reduce support complexity. Besides that, our TMS-RA readily fits into most CA's business models. This feature empowers our partners and customers. The business model and branding strategy technically streamlines a value-adding, outstanding solution provider.
	</p>
	<p>
	Visit <a href="http://www.securemetric.com">www.securemetric.com</a> for more information.
	</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Feitian">
	<p>
	<a href="http://www.ftsafe.com">Feitian</a> is dedicated to being the leading innovator of smartcard and chip operating system based security technologies and applications.
	Feitian's major business covers Strong Authentication, Software Protection, Smartcard COS and Peripherals. 
	You can get more information about Feitian at <a href="http://www.ftsafe.com">www.ftsafe.com</a>.
	</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Aventra MyEID">
<p>The Aventra MyEID card is a smart card that works on most platforms, including windows and linux. You can order MyEID cards from the <a href="https://services.aventra.fi/webshop/">Aventra Webshop</a>.</p>
</subsection>


</section>

<section name="Token Management">
    <p>
    EJBCA can also be used with numerous products (free or non-free) for token management. Some software supported by the respective vendors, and used in production with EJBCA, are listed below.
    </p>

<subsection name="SecureMetric">
	<p>
	<a href="http://www.securemetric.com">SecureMetric</a> has over 13 years experience in serving clients across the world and the market leader in the Smart Card and Cryptographic Token industry for the Southeast Asian region. Our flagship SecureToken ST3 is a lightweight PKI token that is cost effective and has been proven to work better than other well known international brands.
	</p>
	<p>
	When deployed together with our Token Management and Registration Authority (TMS-RA) system, we are able to unify the separated Certificate and Token life cycles into a single management system which allows operators to better manage their clients and reduce support complexity. Besides that, our TMS-RA readily fits into most CA's business models. This feature empowers our partners and customers. The business model and branding strategy technically streamlines a value-adding, outstanding solution provider.
	</p>
	<p>
	Visit <a href="http://www.securemetric.com">www.securemetric.com</a> for more information.
	</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="AET SafeSign IC bundle">
<p>
A.E.T. Europe B.V. (AET) is a leading global supplier of strong authentication solutions. 
Our SafeSign Identity Client (IC) is the leading smart card/USB Token middleware available today. 
It is used by millions of people to securely store their digital certificate on smart cards and USB tokens and 
gain access to all kinds of applications and systems, like the Industrial Commercial bank of China (ICBC) and the Dutch UZIpas.
</p><p>
SafeSign IC provides strong authentication, smart card logon, encryption and digital signatures on Windows, 
Linux and MAC. Combined with the CCID compatible steel Marx CrypToken USB token it is a perfect solution to use 
with an EJBCA PKI infrastructure. AET likes to offer EJBCA users the opportunity to evaluate and use the 
SafeSign IC software in combination with a steel, CCID compatible USB token for a special price!
<br/>
Contact <a href="http://www.aeteurope.nl/">AET Europe</a> for more information.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="SecMaker NetID">
<p>
The NetID PKI middleware is a client working on Windows, Linux and Mac OS X. It enables signing, authentication and usage of
certificates in various systems. Distinguishing features of the NetID client is enhanced support in Windows Terminal Server 
and Citrix Presentation Server, as well as support for a variety of different smart cards.
<br/>
Contact <a href="http://www.secmaker.com/">SecMaker</a> for more information.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Aventra Card Management System">
<p>
Aventra Ltd is a company specialized in plastic cards, smart cards, and data security. Among it's products are the Aventra Card Management System and the MyEID multifunctional PKI card. 
<br/>
Contact <a href="http://aventra.fi/English/index_E.php">Aventra</a> for more information.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="GemSAFE Toolbox">
    <p>
    GemSAFE toolbox and tokens are developed by Gemalto. Using this product an
    organization can setup a secure platform for online banking, transaction,
    identity verification and data exchange. It has been adapted by lots of
    well known companies and organizations for instant, Cisco, Airbus, BMW,
    China Construction Bank, Industrial Commercial bank of China (ICBC) and etc.
    </p>
    <p>
    Some of the GemSAFE features:
    <ul>
    <li>Email signature and encryption</li>
    <li>Smartcard logon</li>
    <li>Strong authentication with SSL</li>
    <li>Document signature and encryption</li>
    <li>VB macro signature</li>
    <li>Support 16 languages</li>
    <li>Works with MS Outlook, Thunderbird, Lotus Notes, IE, Netscape, FireFox and more</li>
    </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
	GemSAFE was successfully used together with EJBCA for the ZhuHai Local
	Taxation Bureau project, listed in the <a href="installations.html">reference installations</a> section.
    </p>
    <p>
    There is a howto for using GemSAFE with EJBCA in the <a href="howto.html">Howto</a> section.
    </p>
</subsection>

</section>

  </body>
</document>
