<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Contact &amp; Support</title>
    <description>Get in contact with the authors of EJBCA for contributing, security notices or commercial support.</description>    
  </properties>

  <body>
<section name="Commercial Support">
<p>
<i>Ready-made commercial EJBCA PKI support</i><br/>
<a href="https://www.primekey.se/service-support/support/">Support programs</a> and other qualified 
professional services are provided by <a href="https://www.primekey.se">PrimeKey Solutions AB</a>.
</p>
</section>

<section name="3rd Party Integration">
<p>
Looking to integrate a 3rd party application with EJBCA? EJBCA has the most flexible range of standard, and non standard, protocols for seamless integration.
<br/>Contact <a href="https://www.primekey.se/contact-us/">Primekey</a> if you need more information or assistance.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Security Notifications">
<p>
If you have a security notification regarding EJBCA, please send an email to <i>security at primekey dot se</i>.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Contributors">
<p>
The best way to contact the project administrators is by e-mail.
</p>
<ul>
<li>Send an email to the ejbca-develop <a href="#Mailing Lists">mailing list</a> (see below).</li>
<li>Send an email directly to a project <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ejbca/">administrator</a>.</li>
<li>Send an email to PrimeKey at <i>sales at primekey dot se</i>.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section name="Documentation">
    <p>
First of all, have a look at the EJBCA documentation resources gathered below 
"EJBCA PKI Docs", "EJBCA OCSP Docs" and "Other documentation" in the main menu.

    </p><p>
Secondly, examine the EJBCA <a href="docs/faq.html">FAQ</a>.
    </p>
</section>

<section name="Training">
<p>
<i>Established EJBCA PKI Training</i><br/>
<a href="https://www.primekey.se/service-support/training/">Training Courses</a> for advanced users are held 
internationally by PrimeKey and their partners.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Mailing Lists">
<p>
There are two public EJBCA mailing lists hosted on Sourceforge. To subscribe to 
either list, or browse archived messages, simply click optional link(s) below.
</p>
<p>
The <a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/ejbca-news">ejbca-news</a> list 
delivers information such as the most recent EJBCA releases and important EJBCA 
features. This is a low traffic list.
</p>
<p>
The <a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/ejbca-develop">ejbca-develop</a> list 
is used for technical discussions. Almost anything regarding EJBCA PKI can be posted on this list.
</p>
    </section>

<section name="Discussion Forums">
<p>
There are several public <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ejbca/support">discussion forums</a> 
that are used for EJBCA PKI discussions and requests for help etc. 
</p>
    </section>

<section name="IRC">
<p>
EJBCA community support questions can be asked on the IRC channel (#ejbca) on
irc.freenode.net. A nice and free-of-charge, web-based IRC client is available 
<a href="http://chat.mibbit.com/">here</a>. 
PrimeKey is usually available on the IRC channel during European office hours, 
and occasionally at other times too.

</p>
</section>

  </body>
</document>
