<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Download</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Latest Releases">
    <note>
    If you have problems with any of the download links below or need older releases, try to download through the Sourceforge <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ejbca/files/">download page</a>.
    <br/><br/>
    EJBCA Community 6.5.0.5 is available for  
    <a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/ejbca/files/ejbca6/ejbca_6_5_0/ejbca_ce_6_5.0.5.zip">download</a>.
    <br/>
    SHA1 checksum: e32e065061ef6666d9b10cc6e24522a1d9c7fafb<br/>
    SHA256 checksum: 85c09d584896bef01d207b874c54ae2f994d38dd85b40fd10c21f71f7210be8a
    <br/><br/>
    Cert-cvc library 1.4.5 with support for EAC 2.10 Access Control Templates is now available for <a
    href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/ejbca/files/cert-cvc/cert-cvc-1.4.5/cert-cvc-1.4.5.zip">download</a>.
    <br/>
    SHA1 checksum: 4bcb6a9e4a523e466df90b09035db64467a128c2<br/>
    SHA256 checksum: 0f528ffb093bdeb41c087d65dc008603da0855178be459da36ce0617a52386f3
    </note>
  </section>

  <section name="Virtual Machine for Testing">
  <note>Note that the version on the VM is outdated. We are working on improving Virtual Machine images.
  </note>
  <note>Note that the superadmin and probably TLS server certificate have expired on the testing VM. It is possible to 
  manually renew superadmin using the command line interface. See <a href="docs/userguide.html#Renewing%20Superadmin">Renewing Superadmin</a> in the User Guide.
  </note>
    <p>
    Get a feeling for, and start testing, EJBCA easily by downloading and running our 
    <a href="https://download.primekey.se/public/ejbcav6ce-vm.zip">EJBCAv6 VM</a>, currently not with the latest release of EJBCA though.
    The VM features a full EJBCA Community v6 install, running on JBoss 7.1.1.GA and Java 7, using a <a href="http://www.mariadb.org/" target="_mariadb">MariaDB</a> database backend. 
    It comes with a readme file with instructions and some usage hints. The VM runs on KVM, VirtualBox and VWware<sup>&#174;</sup>. The VM should not be used in production as admin keys are pre-generated, i.e. identical on all VMs.
    <br/>Have fun! 
    </p>
  </section>

  <section name="SVN over HTTPS">
    <p>
    The official "secure" delivery of EJBCA source code is in the <a href="repository.html">repository</a> using svn over https. The certificate is issued to cesecore.eu, which was the consortium behind the Common Criteria certification of EJBCA.
    <br/>
    In the SVN repository you can also find the hashes of release zip files in the history of the file doc/xdocs/site/index.xml.
    </p>
    <p>If you are an Enterprise customer, you may also get an official release from <a href="https://www.primekey.com">PrimeKey</a>.
    </p>
  </section>
 
  <section name="Help and support">
    <p>
    You can find both free and commercial support offerings at the <a href="contact.html">Contact &amp; Support</a> page.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section name="Older releases">
    <p>
    Download any of the source packages from <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ejbca/files/">Sourceforge</a>.
    </p>
  </section>

</body>
</document>

