<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Features</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Features">
    <p>Built on the JEE 5 (EJB 3.0) specification.</p>
<ul>
<li>Flexible, component based architecture.</li>
<li>Using standard, high performance RDBMS for storage.</li>
<li>Multiple CAs and levels of CAs, build a complete infrastructure (or several) within one instance of EJBCA.</li>
<li>Unlimited number of Root CAs and SubCAs. Request cross certificates and bridge certificates from other CAs and Bridge CAs. Issue cross certificates to other CAs.</li>
<li>Get your own CA signed by public recognized CAs such as <a href="http://www.comodo.com/">Comodo</a> or <a href="http://www.t-systems.com/">T-Systems</a>.</li>
<li>Supports RSA key algorithm up to 8192 bits.</li>
<li>Supports DSA key algorithm with 1024 bits.</li>
<li>Supports ECDSA key algorithm with named curves or implicitlyCA.</li>
<li>Support multiple hash algorithms for signatures, MD5, SHA-1, SHA-2.</li>
<li>Compliant with NSA SUITE B algorithms and certificates.</li>
<li>Support for X.509 certificates and Card Verifiable certificates (CVC BSI TR-03110 used by <a href="guides.html#Using%20CVC%20CAs%20for%20EU%20EAC%20ePassports">EU EAC ePassports</a>).</li> 
<li>Standalone or integrated in any JEE application.</li>
<li>Simple installation and configuration.</li>
<li>Powerful Web based administration GUI using strong authentication.</li>
<li>Administration GUI available in several languages - Chinese, English, French, German, Italian, Portuguese, Spanish and Swedish.</li>
<li>Internal log messages are localizable for different languages.</li>
<li>Command line administration for scripts etc.</li>
<li>Web service (WS) interface for remote administration and integration.</li>
<li>Modular API for HSMs. Built in support for nCipher, PrimeCardHSM, SafeNet ProtectServer, SafeNet Luna, Utimaco CryptoServer, AEP Keyper, ARX CoSign and other HSMs with a good PKCS#11 library.</li>
<li>Supports different architectures; all-in-one, clustered, external RA, external OCSP, etc.</li>
<li>Individual enrollment or batch production of certificates.</li>
<li>Server and client certificates can be exported as PKCS12, JKS or PEM.</li>
<li>Browser enrollment with Firefox, IE, etc.</li>
<li>Enrollment for other applications through open APIs and tools.</li>
<li>Enrollment generating complete OpenVPN installers for VPN users.</li>
<li>Mobile enrollment, i.e. iOS using <a href="docs/adminguide.html#Tested devices">SCEP</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.3gpp.org/">3GPP</a>, i.e. LTE/4G, compatible PKI.</li>
<li>Smart card logon certificates.</li>
<li>Notification system for e-mail notification to users and administrators when a user is added or certificates expire etc.</li>
<li>Random or manual password for initial user authentication.</li>
<li>Hard token module for integrating with hard token issuing system (smart cards).</li>
<li>Multiple levels of administrators with specified privileges and roles.</li>
<li>Configurable certificate profiles for different types and contents of certificates.</li>
<li>Standard and custom certificate extensions supported.</li>
<li>Configurable entity profiles for different types of users.</li>
<li>Supports the Simple Certificate Enrollment Protocol (<a href="docs/adminguide.html#Scep">SCEP</a>).</li>
<li>Follows X509 and PKIX (RFC5280) standards where applicable.</li>
<li>Qualified Certificate Statement (RFC3739) for issuing EU/ETSI qualified certificates.</li>
<li>Supports the Online Certificate Status Protocol (<a href="docs/architecture-ocsp.html">OCSP</a> - RFC2560 and RFC5019), including AIA-extension.</li>
<li>Supports RFC4387 for distribution of CA certificates and CRLs over HTTP.</li>
<li>Validation Authority service serving OCSP responses (RFC2560/5019), CA certificates and CRLS (RFC4387).</li> 
<li>Validation Authority and OCSP responder can run integrated with EJBCA or stand alone (clustered) for security, high-performance and high-availability.</li>
<li>External Validation Authority and OCSP responder also works with any other CA than EJBCA and support large scale OCSP deployments.</li>
<li>Simple OCSP client in pure java.</li>
<li>Supports for <a href="docs/adminguide.html#CMP">CMP</a> (RFC4210 and RFC4211).</li>
<li>Supports synchronous XKMS version 2 requests.</li>
<li>Revocation and Certificate Revocation Lists (CRLs).</li>
<li>CRL creation and URL-based CRLDistribution Points according to RFC5280.</li> 
<li>Stores Certificates and CRLs in SQL database, LDAP and/or other custom data source.</li>
<li>Optional multiple publishers for publishing certificates and CRLs in LDAP or legacy databases. Several flexible standard publishers exist to meet different demands.</li>
<li>Supports authentication and publishing of certificates to Microsoft Active Directory.</li>
<li>Possibility for autoenrollment (albeit not using windows standard autoenroll).</li>
<li>Component- and plug-in based architecture  for publishing certificates and CRLs to different sources.</li>
<li>Key recovery module to store private keys for recovery for selected users and certificates.</li>
<li>Integrity protected <a href="docs/adminguide.html#Logging">audit log</a> (log signing).</li>
<li>API for an external RA, restricting in-bound traffic to CA.</li>
<li>Optional approval mechanism so several admins are required to perform an action, a.k.a. dual-authentication.</li>
<li>Component based architecture for various authorization methods of entities when issuing certificates.</li>
<li>Possible to integrate into large java applications for optimal integration into business process.</li>
<li>Deploys easily in a clustered, high availability environment.</li>
<li>Health check service to support efficient clustering and monitoring.</li>
<li>Supports multiple application servers: JBoss, Glassfish and to some extent WebLogic</li>
<li>Supports multiple databases: Hypersoniq, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, DB2, Ingres, MS SQL Server, Derby, Sybase, Informix.</li>
<li>Simple stand-alone <a href="docs/userguide.html#EJBCA%20Batch%20Enrollment%20GUI">batch enrollment GUI</a> for CSRs (webservice RA).</li>
<li>Unique possibility to configure either as fully audited CA or as high speed <a href="docs/adminguide.html#Throw%20away%20CA">certificate factory</a>, with the same level of management features.</li>
</ul>    

  </section>

</body>
</document>

