<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>EJBCA PKI Features</title>
    <description>PKI software with complete features for any type of Enterprise and Government PKI. Flexible configuration and integration to meet your needs.</description>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Features">
      
  <subsection name="PKI system features">
<ul>
<li>Multiple CAs and levels of CAs, build a complete infrastructure (or several) within one instance of EJBCA.</li>
<li>Unlimited number of Root CAs and SubCAs. Request cross certificates and bridge certificates from other CAs and Bridge CAs. Issue cross certificates to other CAs.</li>
<li>Support all common <a href="docs/architecture.html#PKI%20Architectures">PKI Architectures</a>, as well as many uncommon.</li>
<li>Get your own CA signed by public recognized CAs such as <a href="https://www.globalsign.com/">GlobalSign</a>, <a href="http://www.t-systems.com/">T-Systems</a> or <a href="https://www.quovadisglobal.com/">QuoVadis</a>.</li>
<li>Follows X509 and PKIX (RFC5280) standards where applicable.</li>
<li>Supports RSA key algorithm up to 8192 bits.</li>
<li>Supports DSA key algorithm with 1024 bits.</li>
<li>Supports ECDSA key algorithm with named curves or implicitlyCA.</li>
<li>Support multiple hash algorithms for signatures, SHA-1, SHA-2.</li>
<li>Compliant with NSA SUITE B algorithms and certificates.</li>
<li>Support for X.509 certificates and Card Verifiable certificates (CVC BSI TR-03110) used by EU <a href="guides.html#Using%20CVC%20CAs%20for%20EU%20EAC%20ePassports%20(EJBCA%20Enterprise%20only)">EAC ePassports</a> and eIDs.</li>
<li>Supports short and long lived certificates. From infinite validity down to minutes or even seconds.</li> 
<li>Support for Hardware Security Modules (HSMs). Built in support for Thales/nCipher, SafeNet Luna, SafeNet ProtectServer, Utimaco CryptoServer, AEP Keyper, ARX CoSign and other HSMs with a good PKCS#11 library.</li>
<li>Individual enrollment or batch production of certificates.</li>
<li>Issues SSL/TLS certificates that work with all common servers.</li>
<li><a href="docs/userguide.html#End%20Entities">Admin registration</a> and <a href="docs/adminguide.html#Self%20Registration">self-registration</a> work-flows out of the box. Supports virtually any work-flow with <a href="docs/adminguide.html#Customizing%20EJBCA">plug-ins</a> and integration.</li>
<li>Server and client certificates can be exported as PKCS12, JKS or PEM.</li>
<li>Easy to use RA web UI for self registration and issuance by administrators.</li>
<li>Legacy browser enrollment with Firefox.</li>
<li>Enrollment for other applications through open APIs and tools.</li>
<li>Enrollment generating complete OpenVPN installers for VPN users.</li>
<li>Mobile enrollment, i.e. iOS using <a href="docs/adminguide.html#Tested devices">SCEP</a>.</li>
<li>Revocation and Certificate Revocation Lists (CRLs).</li>
<li>CRL creation and URL-based CRLDistribution Points according to RFC5280.</li> 
<li>Smart card logon certificates for Windows, Linux and Mac OS X.</li>
<li>Configurable certificate profiles for different types and contents of certificates.</li>
<li>Standard and custom certificate extensions supported.</li>
<li>Supports the Simple Certificate Enrollment Protocol (<a href="docs/adminguide.html#Scep">SCEP</a>).</li>
<li>Qualified Certificate Statement (RFC3739) for issuing EU/ETSI qualified certificates.</li>
<li>Supports the Online Certificate Status Protocol (<a href="docs/architecture-ocsp.html">OCSP</a> - RFC2560, RFC6960 and RFC5019), including AIA-extension.</li>
<li>Supports RFC4387 for distribution of CA certificates and CRLs over HTTP.</li>
<li>Support for RFC4683, Subject Identification Method (SIM).</li>
<li>Validation Authority service serving OCSP responses (RFC2560/5019), CA certificates and CRLS (RFC4387).</li>
<li>Supports the German <a href="http://www.t7ev.org/T7-de/Common-PKI">Common PKI</a> SigG CertHash OCSP extension.</li> 
<li>Supports <a href="docs/adminguide.html#CMP">CMP</a> (RFC4210 and RFC4211).</li>
<li>Key recovery to store private keys for recovery for selected users and certificates.</li>
</ul>    
</subsection>
  <subsection name="ePassport, eID and eDL PKI features">
<ul>
<li>Support for BAC PKI, Country Signing CA (CSCA) and Document Signer (DS) certificates.</li>
<li>Integration with <a href="https://www.signserver.org" target="signserver">SignServer</a> as Document Signer creating Security Objects (SOD).</li>
<li>Support for EAC PKI (EJBCA Enterprise only).</li>
<li>Integration with PrimeKey SPOC for a Single Point of Contact between countries.</li>
<li>Publisher for ICAO PKD, publishing DS certificates and CSCA CRLs to ICAO PKD LDAP directory.</li>
<li>Support ISO 18013 Amendment 2 eDL (Driver License).</li> 
</ul>
  </subsection>  
  <subsection name="Integration features">
<ul>
<li>Built on the JEE 6 specification.</li>
<li>Flexible, component based architecture.</li>
<li>Run standalone or integrated in any JEE application.</li>
<li>External Validation Authority and OCSP responder also works with any other CA than EJBCA and support large scale OCSP deployments.</li>
<li>Validation Authority and OCSP responder can run integrated with EJBCA or stand alone (clustered) for security, high-performance and high-availability.</li>
<li>Simple OCSP client in pure java.</li>
<li><a href="docs/adminguide.html#EJBCA%20plugin%20build%20system">Plug-in functionality</a> allowing you to enhance with your own functionality and work flows.</li>
<li>Web service (WS) interface for remote administration and integration.</li>
<li>Command line interface for scripts etc.</li>
<li>Administration GUI localizable and available in several languages - Japaneese, English, French, German, Italian, Portuguese, Spanish, Chinese, ...</li>
<li>Internal log messages are localizable for different languages.</li>
<li>Component- and plug-in based architecture for publishing certificates and CRLs to different sources.</li>
<li>API for an external RA, restricting in-bound traffic to CA.</li>
<li>Hard token module for integrating with hard token issuing system (smart cards).</li>
</ul>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Administration features">
<ul>
<li>Simple installation and configuration.</li>
<li>Administration through Web GUI, command line or Web Services.</li>
<li>Powerful Web based administration GUI using strong authentication.</li>
<li>Easy to use RA web UI for self registration and issuance by administrators.</li>
<li>Configurable entity profiles for different types of users.</li>
<li>Notification system for e-mail notification to users and administrators when a user is added or certificates expire etc.</li>
<li>Random or manual password for initial user authentication.</li>
<li>Multiple levels of administrators with specified privileges and roles.</li>
<li>Authentication of local CLI users enabling role separation also for local CLI.</li>
<li>Stores Certificates and CRLs in SQL database, LDAP and/or other custom data source.</li>
<li>OCSP transaction logging suitable for statistics and billing.</li>
<li>Optional multiple publishers for publishing certificates and CRLs in LDAP or legacy databases. Several flexible standard publishers exist to meet different demands.</li>
<li>Supports authentication and publishing of certificates to Microsoft Active Directory.</li>
<li>Optional approval mechanism so several admins are required to perform an action, a.k.a. dual-authentication.</li>
<li>Component based architecture for various authorization methods of entities when issuing certificates.</li>
<li>Simple stand-alone <a href="docs/userguide.html#EJBCA%20Batch%20Enrollment%20GUI">batch enrollment GUI</a> for CSRs (webservice RA).</li>
<li>Possibility for autoenrollment, using scripts and APIs.</li>
<li>Easy upgrade paths when new versions are released.</li>
</ul>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="System features">
<ul>
<li>Written in pure Java, running in a JEE application server. Interfaces with Hardware Security Modules using standard PKCS#11 interface.</li>
<li>High performance and capacity, issue hundreds of certificates per second, store hundreds of millions of certificates.</li>
<li>Stress test and performance measuring tools in <a href="docs/userguide.html#EJBCA%20client%20toolbox">client toolbox</a>.</li>
<li>Using standard, high performance RDBMS for storage. Easy to understand and manage.</li>
<li>Supports different architectures; all-in-one, clustered, external RA, external OCSP, etc.</li>
<li>Possible to integrate into large java applications for optimal integration into business process.</li>
<li>Deploys easily in a clustered, high availability environment.</li>
<li>Health check monitoring service to support efficient clustering and monitoring.</li>
<li>Supports multiple application servers: JBoss and Glassfish</li>
<li>Supports multiple databases: Hypersoniq, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, DB2, MS SQL Server, Derby, Sybase, Informix.</li>
<li>Unique possibility to configure either as fully audited CA or as high speed <a href="docs/adminguide.html#Throw%20away%20CA">certificate factory</a>, with the same level of management features.</li>
</ul>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Enterprise Edition features">
<ul>
<li>Support and maintenance from PrimeKey, world renowned PKI experts.</li>
<li>Regular maintenance and security releases.</li>
<li>Common Criteria EAL4+ certified.</li>
<li>Used in many WebTrust, CWA 14167 and eIDAS audited installations.</li>
<li>Integrity protected <a href="docs/adminguide.html#Logging">audit log</a> (log signing), with digital signature or HMAC protection.</li>
<li>Full database integrity protection of all tables, to detect database manipulation.</li>
<li>Command line tool for verification of audit and database integrity protection.</li>
<li>Validation tool for conformance checking of certificates and OCSP responders.</li>
<li>EAC PKI (EAC 1.11 and 2.10) for ePassports and eIDs, Country Verifying CA (CVCA) and Document Verifiers (DV) issuing Inspection System (IS) certificates.</li>
<li>Certified access control and authorization module, for assurance and high trust role separation.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.3gpp.org/">3GPP</a>, i.e. LTE/4G, compatible PKI, using <a href="docs/adminguide.html#CMP">CMP</a> with multiple Vendor CAs and vendor certificate authentication.</li>
<li><a href="docs/adminguide.html#CMP%20Proxy%20(EJBCA%20Enterprise%20only)">CMP Proxy</a> to add an additional network layer, with message check, between the CA and CMP clients.</li>
<li>Command line CMP client in Java useful for scripting, testing and prototyping.</li>
<li><a href="docs/adminguide.html#Configuration">SCEP RA mode</a>, using SCEP controlling entity creation from an RA.</li>
<li><a href="docs/adminguide.html#Configuration">SCEP Client Certificate Renewal</a>, allowing client certificate renewal using SCEP</li>
<li><a href="docs/adminguide.html#Certificate%20Transparency%20(Enterprise%20only)">Certificate Transparency</a>, RFC6962.</li>
<li><a href="docs/adminguide.html#Cert%20Safe%20publisher%20for%20a%20HTTPS%20server%20(Enterprise%20only)">CertSafe</a> publisher to send, and revoke, certificates from a CertSafe server.</li>
<li><a href="docs/userguide.html#Managing EJBCA Peer Systems">Peer Connectors</a> for managing Peer Systems, such as OCSP Responders.</li>
<li>Direct Validation Authority (OCSP responder) updates from CA to VA. Ideal for low latency revocation and white listing.</li>
<li><a href="docs/externalra.html">External RA</a> with a polling model for RA to CA communication, for high security environments. Ability to run the RA web UI in polling mode.</li>
<li>Create Crypto Tokens and CAs, generate keys and add and remove administrators through the Web Service API.</li>
<li>EV Certificate specific DN components as defined in CABForum guidelines (jurisdictionLocality, State and Country).</li>
<li>eIDAS specific fields as defined in ETSI EN 319 412 (organizationIdentifier).</li>
<li>Additional algorithms using HSMs through PKCS#11, <a href="docs/adminguide.html#Using%20SHA256WithRSAandMGF1%20(RSASSA-PSS)">RSASSA-PSS (SHA256WithRSAAndMGF1)</a>. Available through patches for Java.</li>
<li>Support for Native MS Autoenrollment in Windows environment with add-on autoenrollment proxy module.</li>
<li>Support for GOST and DSTU algorithms (Russian and Ukrainian algorithms).</li>
<li>Penetration tested with improved security.</li>
</ul>
  </subsection>
  </section>

</body>
</document>

