<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Home</title>
    <description>EJBCA PKI Certificate Authority software and appliance. Setting up a scalable and flexible PKI for enterprise, government, mobile and IoT.</description>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="">

<div class="frame">
<div class="label">
      EJBCA release news &amp; other marvels
</div>
<div id="news">
    <!--TWITTER WIDGET-->
<div id="twitter">
<a class="twitter-timeline" href="https://twitter.com/primekeyPKI" data-widget-id="344774465936306176" width="260" height="295" data-dnt="true">Tweets by @primekeyPKI</a>
<script type="text/javascript">
!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+"://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");
</script>
</div>
 <div>  
  <p><strong>EJBCA Enterprise 6.6.2 has now been released.</strong>
 PrimeKey's <a href="https://www.primekey.se/technologies/products-overview/ejbca-enterprise/">EJBCA Enterprise</a> is Common Criteria EAL4+ certified and CWA/ETSI compliant to provide the most powerful and flexible PKI. For entire non-community features, only available in EJBCA Enterprise, see the section on <a href="features.html#Enterprise%20Edition%20features">"Enterprise Edition features" in the features list</a>.
  <br /><span class="date"> Posted: 2016-12-04</span>
  </p>
 <p><strong>EJBCA Community 6.3.1.1 is now out!</strong> The next generation open source PKI is here, supporting Java 7, JBoss 7 and new advanced features.
  Visit the <a href="download.html">download</a> section. There you will also find a pre-installed VM to try (not necessarily with the latest version though).
  <br /><span class="date"> Posted: 2015-06-02</span>  
  </p>  
    <p><strong>EJBCA Tech Blog!</strong> <a href="http://blog.ejbca.org" target="ejbcablog">What does eIDAS compliance mean for a PKI?</a> 
  <br /><span class="date"> Posted: 2016-05-18</span>
  </p> 
  <p><strong>PKI-in-a-box!</strong> By integrating secure hardware technology with the flexibility, reliability and feature set of EJBCA Enterprise, 
  the turnkey PKI Appliance features an easy to install PKI-in-a-box, offering predictable costs and increased quality to your PKI solution. Check out the simpler, yet safer, <a href="https://www.primekey.se/technologies/products-overview/pki-appliance/?pk_campaign=org&amp;pk_kwd=box">PrimeKey PKI Appliance</a>.
  </p>   
  <p>
  </p>
  </div>
</div>
</div> 

  </section>

<section name="EJBCA PKI CA">
<p>
EJBCA<sup>&#174;</sup> is a PKI Certificate Authority software, built using Java (JEE) technology. 
Robust, flexible, high performance, scalable, platform independent, and component based, EJBCA can be used stand-alone or integrated with other applications.
</p>
<p>
Being extremely scalable and flexible, EJBCA is suitable to build a complete PKI infrastructure for any large enterprise or organization. If you only want to 
issue a few single certificates for testing, there are probably other options that will get you started quicker, but if you want a serious Certificate Authority 
to manage your Public Key Infrastructure, we recommend EJBCA. 
<br/>Investigate the links below to understand more what EJBCA really is.
</p>
<ul>
<li>A <a href="docs/installation.html">Certificate Authority</a> (link to documentation site).</li>
<li>A <a href="docs/services-va.html">Validation Authority</a> (link to documentation site).</li>
<li>An <a href="docs/architecture-ocsp.html">OCSP Responder</a> (link to documentation site).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>EJBCA has everything for your trust center.</strong> Contact us for more info, or look at the full (but never complete) <a href="features.html">features list</a>.</p>
<subsection name="Certificate issuance">
<p>
Example uses cases (non-exhaustive) where EJBCA is used to issue certificates are:
</p>
<ul>
<li>PKI Trust and Certificate service providers, WebTrust and ETSI (including eIDAS) compliant.</li>
<li>Strong authentication for users accessing your intranet/extranet/internet resources.</li>
<li>Secure communication with SSL/TLS servers and SSL/TLS clients. EJBCA is an excellent SSL PKI.</li>
<li><a href="complementary.html#Token Management">Smart card and token management</a>.</li>
<li><a href="guides.html#Microsoft smart card logon">Smart card logon</a> to Windows and/or Linux.</li>
<li>Linux autoenrollment, Windows autoenrollment, automated secure VM deployment, and more.</li>
<li>Signing and encrypting email (SMIME).</li>
<li>VPN connections by issuing certificates to your VPN routers such as OpenVPN, Cisco, Juniper etc.</li>
<li>Client VPN access with certificates in users VPN clients.</li>
<li>Network authentication with 802.1x.</li>
<li>Single sign-on by using a single certificate to secure logon to web applications.</li>
<li>Creating signed documents.</li>
<li>Mobile PKI, <a href="docs/adminguide.html#iPhone/iOS">enrolling iOS</a> etc.</li>
<li>Secure mobile networks, i.e. 3GPP/LTE/4G using the <a href="docs/adminguide.html#CMP">CMP protocol</a>.</li>
<li>Counterfeit prevention by signing and pairing accessories.</li>
<li>Internet of Things (IoT). Need some hundreds of millions of certificates fast? EJBCA will handle it.</li>
<li>Mobile Device Management (MdM) and Enterprise Mobility Management (EMM).</li>
<li>Issue citizen certificates for access to government resources, used in passports etc.</li>
<li>CVCAs and DVs and issue CV certificates (CVC) to Document Verifiers and Inspection Systems for <a href="docs/cvccas.html">EAC ePassports</a>, eIDs and eDL.</li>
<li>... and many many more ...</li>
</ul>
</subsection>
<note>
You can also use EJBCA to set up a CA independent, high performance, highly available OCSP responder service.
</note>
<p style="margin-top:1em;">Together with sister projects (see <i><a href="complementary.html">Complementary software</a></i>) of EJBCA you can also:</p>
<ul>
<li>Get central trusted <a href="https://signserver.org">Time Stamps</a> for you electronically signed documents.</li>
<li>Perform <a href="https://signserver.org">central signing of documents</a>.</li>
<li>Sign electronic passport data (MRTD).</li>
<li>Issue hard tokens (<a href="complementary.html#Hardware%20tokens">smart cards</a>) and manage the complete life cycle of cards and certificates.</li>
<li>... and many many more ...</li>
</ul>
  <note>
  The cert-cvc library handles CVC certificates for EU EAC ePassport PKIs and the current release is 
  feature complete for EU EAC ePassports using all algorithms.
  <br/>
  The library is freely usable under the LGPL 2.1 (or later) license for all parties interesting 
  in handling CVC certificates, in particular for EU EAC ePassports. 
  The cert-cvc library was donated to the open source by the Swedish National Police Board. 
  </note>
</section>
<section name="Open Source PKI">
<p>
This PKI software is OSI Certified Open Source Software licensed under the <em>LGPL v2.1 or later</em> license.
OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.
</p>
<p>
The source code of EJBCA Community is hosted on a (mostly) public <a href="https://svn.cesecore.eu/svn/ejbca/">svn</a> and all downloads include the complete source code and can be downloaded from <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ejbca/">Sourceforge.net</a>.
<br></br>
If you want to contribute to EJBCA, please see <i><a href="contributions.html">Contribute to EJBCA</a></i>
<br></br>
You can also donate to EJBCA, please see <i><a href="donations.html">Donate to EJBCA</a></i>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Support and development">
<p>EJBCA Enterprise with commercial support, development, integration and maintenance is available through <a href="https://www.primekey.se/">PrimeKey Solutions</a>. 
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

