<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Reference installations</title>
    <description>View a small sample selection of use cases where EJBCA PKI is installed.</description>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Thousands of installations">
  <p>EJBCA is downloaded thousands of times every month, and is used in thousands of organizations around the world. Ranging from installations in small companies, to 
  missions critical installations in multinational companies and governments. If you have a use case for PKI, there is a good chance someone else is already using it for just that.</p>
  </section>
  <section name="Commercial references">
  <p>
  PrimeKey has a list of <a href="https://www.primekey.com/customers/">commercial business cases</a> where PrimeKey is involved. This list is continuously growing as we produce new material.
  </p>
  </section>
  <section name="Reference installations">
	<p>This section lists a limited selection of sites where EJBCA have been deployed successfully.
	As any software installations things move around over time, so the number of users etc should be considered an indication, not an absolute number.
	</p>
	<p>
	If you would allow us to present you on the list of reference installations, please <a href="contact.html">contact</a> us.
	</p>
	
	<subsection name="PrimeKey Solutions AB">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: Stockholm, Sweden</li>
    <li>Installed by: <a href="https://www.primekey.com/">PrimeKey Solutions AB</a></li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: IT-Security</li>
    <li>Solution 1: Internal CA. Operational since 2002. Using EJBCA to authenticate users for access to internal web services and email both from internal network and from internet. Issues both smart cards (using PrimeCard) and soft tokens to users.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Less than 100</li>
    <li>Solution 2: External CA. Operational since 2004. Using EJBCA for partners and demo purposes. Each partner have their own SubCA and all CAs uses smart card HSM for protection of CA private keys. Issues both smart cards (using PrimeCard or manual enrollment using different CSPs) and soft tokens to users.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Less than 100</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="Ministry of Defence, France">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: France</li>
    <li>Installed by: <a href="http://www.linagora.fr/">Linagora S.A</a> with support from PrimeKey Solutions AB</li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Defence (Public Sector)</li>
    <li>Solution: Operational since april 2005. Backup PKI infrastructure. Uses nCipher HSM for CA key storage at root CA, and have several sub CAs. Issues soft tokens (pkcs12) to users using browsers and email clients.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Up to 1000 in the first phase</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="Ministry of finances, France">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: France</li>
    <li>Installed by: <a href="http://www.linagora.fr/">Linagora S.A</a></li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Taxation (Public Sector)</li>
    <li>Solution: Operational since october 2005. 3 CA and 1 sub CA. Issues soft tokens (pkcs12) for servers, issues certificates to users using browsers for authentication.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Up to 40000 in the first phase</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="KG Knutsson AB">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Organization: <a href="http://www.kgk.se/">KG Knutsson AB</a></li>
	<li>Location: Sweden</li>
    <li>Installed by: <a href="https://www.primekey.com/">PrimeKey Solutions AB</a></li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Trade and Commerce</li>
    <li>Solution: Pilot installation. Operational since dec 2004. Using EJBCA for issuing digital certificates. In combination with smart cards. Advanced setup with smart cards used for login to Active Directory infrastructure, browsers and email clients. Special use is key backup and recovery.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Up to 1000</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="National Swedish Police Board">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: Sweden</li>
    <li>Installed by: <a href="https://www.primekey.com/">PrimeKey Solutions AB</a></li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Public Sector</li>
    <li>Solution 1: Pilot installation. Operational since 2005. Using EJBCA for issuing certificates for VPN purposes.</li>
    <li>Solution 2: Production installation. Operational since 2005. Using EJBCA for issuing certificates for Microsoft Logon Certificates.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Up to 25000 users</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="ZhuHai Local Taxation Bureau">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Organization: ZhuHai Local Taxation Bureau</li>
	<li>Location: ZhuHai city, GuangDong province, China</li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Govermental authority (Taxation)</li>
    <li>Solution: Operational since 2003. Use EJBCA as user database for Websphere. Login to application with forms and XML-signatures created using smart cards with certificates from EJBCA.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Up to 25000 in the first phase. Another 25000 users was added in the second phase 2008.</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="Grupo Safa">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: Spain</li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Health Care (Pharmaceutical area)/Public Sector</li>
    <li>Solution: Are using EJBCA to generate digital certificates internally and to their customers through a B2B-portal.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Up to 20000</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="Serasa.com">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: Brazil</li>
	<li>Installed by: <a href="http://www.serasaexperian.com.br/">Serasa.com</a></li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Financial/Public sector</li>
    <li>Solution: Operational since 2004. Are using EJBCA to generate digital certificates to the financial sector.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Up to 20000</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="Evaltec">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: Brazil</li>
	<li>Installed by: <a href="http://www.iqualy.com/">Iqualy.com</a></li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Bank and Finance</li>
    <li>Solution: Operational since 2004. Using EJBCA for issuing digital certificates (soft tokens).</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Unknown</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="Concealed customer">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: Sweden</li>
    <li>Installed by: <a href="https://www.primekey.com/">PrimeKey Solutions AB</a></li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Public Sector</li>
    <li>Solution: Operational since feb 2003. Uses smart cards issued to employees. Advanced setup with smart cards used for login to Active Directory infrastructure, browsers and email clients. Special use is key backup and recovery.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Up to 1000</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>
	
	<subsection name="Fimasys">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: Suresnes, France</li>
    <li>Installed by: <a href="email:asyd@solaris-fr.org">Bruno Bonfils</a></li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Financial (Application Editor)</li>
    <li>Solution: VPN identities, server and user certificates (X.509 authentication).</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Unknown</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="ACCV">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Location: Region of Valencia, Spain (www.accv.es)</li>
    <li>Installed by: <a href="http://www.accv.es/">ACCV</a></li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Certification Service Provider for Public Administrations and citizens</li>
    <li>Count of Users: Expected, more than 200.000. Currently (juny 2006) 75.200</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>

	<subsection name="Infrax d.o.o">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Organization: Infrax d.o.o. (http://www.infrax.si)</li>
	<li>Location: Slovenia</li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: IT</li>
    <li>Solution: Operational since june 2005, 1 CA and 4 SubCAs. Primarily issue certificates for OpenVPN clients (and servers)and for web and mail servers.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: less than 100</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>
	
	<subsection name="Edicom">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Organization: Edicom (http://www.edicomgroup.com/)</li>
	<li>Location: Spain</li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: Telecom</li>
    <li>Solution: Installation certified by ASIMELEC according to ETSI TS 101 456 since 2008-10-13.
    	Used for issuing Qualified Certificates for eInvoicing throughout Europe.</li>
    <li>Count of end entities: Less than 100 in the first phase.</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>
	
	<subsection name="Zurich University of Applied Sciences">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Organization: Zurich University of Applied Sciences (http://www.zhaw.ch/)</li>
	<li>Location: Winterthur, Switzerland</li>
    <li>Trade of Industry: University</li>
    <li>Installed by: Marc Rennhard, Alexander Horvath</li>
    <li>Solution: Operational since 2007. Used as a backend for the Institute's (http://init.zhaw.ch) certificate services,
        specially for email encryption. Basically it is operated for research purposes.</li>
    <li>Count of Users: around 50</li>
    </ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>
	
	<subsection name="Virginia Tech Certification Authority">
	<p>
	<ul>
	<li>Organization: Virginia Tech (http://www.vt.edu/)</li>
	<li>Location: USA</li>
	<li>Trade of Industry: University</li>
	<li>Solution: Globally trusted PKI, chained to GlobalSign. <a href="http://www.pki.vt.edu/">http://www.pki.vt.edu/</a></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	</subsection>
  </section>

</body>
</document>

