<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Release cycle</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="EJBCA release cycle">
	  <p>
	  The EJBCA release numbering is on the form EJBCA x.y.z.w (for example 6.3.1.1) where the numbering follows these rules:  
	  </p>
	  <ul>
	  <li>Major Release (x): The first number indicates a major paradigm shift. Examples are moving from one EJB standard to the next (ejb3 -> ejb3 etc) or making the shift from 
	  a single CA per installation to multiple CAs, something that changes how you work with EJBCA. These shift are very rare with many years between them. A major release probably requires major upgrade activities.</li>
	  <li>Feature Release (y): The second number corresponds to major enhancements in terms of functionality, or of significant upgrade of embedded component versions. 
	  These releases may occur once or twice a year, or it may also be longer between them. A major feature may require database upgrades, where upgrade scripts are provided.</li>
	  <li>Minor Release (z): The third number corresponds to minor upgrades with regards to bugfixes and functionality enhancements.
	  A minor release should not require database upgrades. Minor releases are usually plug-in upgrades and occurs frequently, several times each year.</li>
	  <li>Maintenance Release (w): The fourth number corresponds to a maintenance release that contains important bugfixes, or other cherry picked changes, to a stable release branch.
	  Maintenance releases are plug-in upgrades and only occur when needed.</li>
	  </ul>
	  <p>
	  A branch in the version control system is always created when a Major or Feature release is done. The branch name corresponds to the version, e.g. Branch_6_6.
	  Minor and Maintenance releases are always made from a branch.
	  </p><p>
	  All releases are tagged with the release number and date in the version control system, e.g. EJBCA_6_3_1_1-20150601, although tags are typically not publicly visible.
	  Some releases may be tagged but not released when it is a single fix for a specific user where the fix is not deemed of interest for a broader audience.
	  </p>
  </section>

</body>
</document>

