<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>A short course on certificates</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Identity certificates">
	<p>
	Currently there are three certificates involved in each secure Web transaction.
      <ul>
        <li>Server certificate: Attests to the identity of the Web server owner.</li>
        <li>Client certificate: Attests to the identity of the Web user (customer).</li>
        <li>Certificate authority certificate: Attests to the identity of the certificate authority (CA) that signed the server and client certificates.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
	In principal, there is a root CA
	certificate that is self signed and that everyone trusts. If the root
	CA certificate is compromised, the whole certificate structure falls
	apart. It is perhaps a philosophical issue, but the original goal of a
	certificate authority hierarchy, which would allow each certificate to
	be traced up to the root CA, was never established because the notion
	of an identity does not scale well. In a small community, everyone
	knows everyone else so the binding of a name to an identity is not
	difficult. However, if your friend John Smith moved to New York City,
	it will be very difficult to know which John Smith in the telephone
	book is your friend. Fortunately, the SensorNet community is smaller
	and most users will have government-issued credentials to vouch for
	their identities, so we can be confident of identities. For SensorNet,
	less formal measures are called for. SensorNet is its own root CA and
	has self signed the SensorNetCA certificate (in the name of SensorNet).
	Due care is taken to keep the CA computer backed up and locked up in a
	secure location. This is the correct thing to do because for our
	purposes, we trust ourselves more than we trust an external CA such as
	VeriSign.
	</p>

      <p>
	The format for identity
	certificates is spelled out in the PKI (public key infrastructure)
	specifications called X.509. Currently, the certificates we issue
	correspond to the latest, version 3 specification. These certificates
	bind an identity in the real world to a public key. For our purposes,
	our unique identity is specified by what is called a distinguished name
	(DN) which is composed of a person's real name, country, organization,
	organizational unit, city, state, and e-mail address. However, since
	certificates can also be issued to computers and other non-human
	entities, the notion of an identity is actually broader and fuzzier
	than might be ideal. An X.509v3 certificate allows a certificate holder
	to create a digital signature, to use the keys for encryption, to
	create S/MIME e-mail, and to sign trusted objects (e.g., Active-X
	controls). These privileges are actually delegated separately by
	different bits in the certificate's extensions. The contents of my
	SensorNet certificate show that I can use my certificate as an SSL
	client, for secure E-mail, and for object signing.
	</p>

</section>
<section name="Uses of identity certificates">
	<p>
	Once you have an identity
	certificate, what good is it? Here are some of the things you can do
	with your certificate:
	</p>
	<subsection name="Secure Web access">
	<p>
	Identity certificates allow user-friendly, secure access to a Web site
	with strong authentication. Modern Web servers (Netscape, IIS, Apache)
	can all be set up to require client certificates for site access. Out
	of the box, it is trivial to configure the server to accept only
	SensorNet certificates, so that anyone with a valid SensorNet
	certificate will be authenticated securely and can use SSL for secure
	access. No user ids and passwords are required. However, once per
	browser session, the user will have to unlock his private certificate
	key with a local password. The SensorNet CA web site is set up this way
	on a Tomcat server.
	</p>
	<p>
	Access to a site can also be
	controlled by using "basic" authentication (user ids and passwords).
	There are several problems with this
	approach. The biggest problem is that this solution does not scale
	well. If a new user is added and we used basic authentication, we would
	have to enroll the user separately at each server. Then there is the
	problem of allowing the user to securely set his password on each of
	these machines, especially if you do not want to give the user a login
	account on the machine (an invitation to a security breach). With
	SensorNet issued certificates, new users are automatically granted
	access to all SensorNet sites requiring certificates for access.
	</p>
	<p>
	Passwords also present several security problems. If the host computer gets hacked, the (hashed)
	password file may become compromised (thus allowing offline brute force
	attacks) requiring that all users get new passwords. This has proved to
	be a logistical problem. Passwords can be easily sniffed if the user's
	computer gets hacked, and
	good passwords are hard to remember and thus get written down on
	stickys attached to the computer for all to see. There is also
	generally no restriction to the number of times that a password-based
	Web access pop up can fail (or else there could be easy denial of
	service attacks). Therefore, access via user id and password is subject
	to password guessing attacks.
	</p>
	</subsection>
	<subsection name="Digital signatures">
	<p>
	Client certificates allow users to sign things, solving the
	authenticity security requirement. It is very easy to spoof E-mail, so
	it is good practice to sign all electronic communications. The PGP
	community has been routinely signing all their mail for years, but I
	feel that the X.509 solution scales better and more user friendly than
	PGP.
	</p>
	<p>
	PGP uses identity certificates
	also. However, PGP certificates are not signed by a CA. They are signed
	by your friends and acquaintances, or other people who vouch for your
	identity. This is called the "web of trust" model. X.509 certificates
	are signed by a CA that presumably you trust. There is much less
	baggage associated with X.509 because you do not have to go to key
	signing parties to get your PKI key well validated -- That is the
	function of the CA.
	</p>
	</subsection>
	<subsection name="Digital signatures">
	<p>
	Your public key is your cyber identity. It can be used in other
	contexts to grant you authority to do things. The concept of authority
	certificates is the basis for the SPKI (simple public key
	infrastructure) that is currently in an IETF draft. See <a
	 href="http://theworld.com/%7Ecme/html/spki.html">http://theworld.com/~cme/html/spki.html</a>.
	Provided that you can access your private key to unlock your
	certificate (to prevent spoofing), extremely complicated security
	policies can be implemented using a collection of authorization
	certificates.
	</p>
	</subsection>
	<subsection name="S/MIME e-mail">
	<p>
	S/MIME is a specification for secure electronic messaging. In 1995, several software vendors got together
	and created S/MIME to solve a very real problem -- interception and forgery of e-mail. Protecting sensitive
	data is a real concern, especially in a world that is becoming increasingly more wired. The goal of S/MIME
	is to make it easy to secure messages from prying eyes. Since its creation, S/MIME has come a long way.
	Most mail clients support S/MIME encrypted and signed e-mail. All of the major industry players have also
	agreed to support the S/MIME standard.  Again, sending secure e-mail is like practicing safe sex - you
	need to do it. Yes, not everything you send needs to be encrypted. However, it is very easy to intercept
	e-mail and to modify it. A malicious entity can put damaging words into your innocent e-mail. In today's
	world, security by obscurity does not work any more.	
	</p>
	</subsection>
	<subsection name="Object signing">
	<p>
	To combat the threat of computer viruses, executable code is now being signed to prove its authenticity
	and integrity. Java applets and Active-X controls are examples of the types of things that should be signed.
	If we create code that runs on a user's machine, it should be signed for both the user's peace of mind and
	for our legal protection. Various PKI tools allows you to use SensorNet Client Certificates for code signing.	
	</p>
	</subsection>
</section>


</body>
</document>

